RG 103, Colt's Patent Fire Arms Manufacturing Company
Connecticut State Library
- Business File, 1826-1979; T001481; 25.75 cubic feet
  - Subgroup 3. Brass Foundry, 1855-1889; 1 folder (Box 29)
    The Brass Foundry, supervised by Thomas Curry, was one of many Colt armory inside contracting operations. Colt supplied the workspace and machinery and in return, experienced workers filled the orders. The owners of large manufacturing interests in the mid-nineteenth century used the inside contractor system to more efficiently run the operation. The owner could devote himself to money matters while skilled specialists saw to the employees and actual production.
    Contains only two items; an account book, 1855-1889 and a diary, 1871. Both were kept by Curry.
  - Subgroup 4. Johns-Pratt Company, 1922-1942; 4 folders (Box 29)
    In an attempt to diversify production, the Colt Company purchased the Johns-Pratt Company in 1923. Located in Hartford on Capitol Avenue, Johns-Pratt had produced electrical and moulded plastic products since 1886. Out of Johns-Pratt, Colt created three new divisions: the Plastics Division, Electrical Division, and the Autosan Dish-washing Machine Division.
    - Johns-Pratt Company, 1 folder (Box 29)
      Contains an accounting firm's report on the Johns-Pratt Company, December 31, 1923; financial statements, income and cash reports, January 1924-January 1926.
    - Plastics Division, 1922-1937; 1 folder (Box 29)
      The Plastics Division was divided into three departments: the button department, mechanical goods department, and general plastics moulding department. The materials in this subgroup contain, an article on the Plastics Division from a November 1936 "Connecticut Industry," and a March 1940 "American Era." Also included are newspaper clippings and an advertising circular.
    - Colt Noark Division (Electrical Division), 1922-1942; 1 folder (Box 29)
      Colt's Electrical Division produced a wide array of fuses, switches, and starters for industrial use.
      Most of the material's on the division in the file are catalogues of products and two newspaper/magazine clippings.
    - Autosan Dish-Washing Machine Division, circa 1935; 1 folder (Box 29)
      First patented in 1913, the Colt Autosan Dish-Washer gained wide acceptance with restaurants and holels during the 1930s. Production continued until circa 1950.
      Records include an instruction and parts booklet and advertising circulars.
  - Subgroup 5. Sonora Mining and Exploring Company, 1858-1861; 1 folder (Box 29)
    Interested in the exploration of the Arizona territory, Samuel Colt founded the Sonora Mining and Exploring Company. He sent his secretary, J.D. Alden; his agent, W.B. Hartley; and his brother-in-law, R.W.H. Jarvis to Arizona to investigate land expansion and mining possibilities. The Sonora Mining and Exploring Company shared board members and some stockholders with the Colt Company.
    The subgroup contains correspondence, 1858-1861 form Colt's men in Arizona as well as letters to Board of Directors and stockholders. Also contains H.R. 836, January 1859, a bill to provide temporary government for the Territory of Arizona. Also S. 555, February 1859, a bill to provide temporary government for the Dakota and Arizona territories.
  - Subgroup 6. Union Ferry Company, 1857-1875 (Box 30)
    The Union Ferry Company was incorporated in 1857 for the purpose of operating a ferry across the Connecticut River between Hartford and East Hartford. Samuel Colt was elected a director of the company in August, 1858, and was the company's single largest stockholder.
    - Series 1. Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 30)
      Arranged in chronological order by type of correspondence.
      - Outgoing, 1858 October-1859 October (Box 30)
      - Incoming, 1858 January-1864 November (Box 30)
    - Series 2. Corporate Legal Records, 2 folders (Box 30)
      Contains the act incorporating the Union Ferry Company in May, 1857.
      - Record of Incorporation, 1857 May (Box 30)
      - Corporate papers and by-laws (Box 30)
        Contains a record book with minutes of Board of Director's meetings, July 1857-March 1867, corporate by-laws and legal correspondence, lists of stockholders, and certificates for shares of stock, 1858.
    - Series 3. Financial Records, 8 volumes (Box 30)
      Contains a fairly complete records of the company's finances.
      - Bank account book, 1858-1875 (Box 30)
      - Daybook, 1858-1875 (Box 30)
      - Daybook, 1858-1866 (Box 30)
      - Trial balances and Treasurer's Reports, 1859-1867 (Box 30)
        Contains accounts of the Union Ferry Comapny with the Colt Company, indicating that there was some exchange of labor and storage between the two.
      - Record Book, 1857-1869 (Box 30A)
      - Ledger, 1858-1866 (Box 30B)
      - Cash book, 1858-1866 (Box 30C)
      - Journal, 1859-1866 (Box 30D)
    - Series 4. Passenger Logs, 10 volumes (Box 31)
      Contains ten volumes listing the horse teams, wagons, ox teams and foot passengers ferried across the river. Volume one is missing.
      - Volume 2, 1863 July-December (Box 31)
      - Volume 3, 1863 September-1864 September (Box 31)
      - Volume 4, 1864 September-1865 September (Box 31)
      - Volume 5, 1866 November-December (Box 31)
      - Volume 6, 1867 March-October (Box 31)
      - Volume 7, 1867 May-June (Box 31)
      - Volume 8, 1867 April-September (Box 31)
      - Volume 9, 1870 December-1871 October (Box 32)
      - Volume 10, 1871 October-1872 September (Box 32)
      - Volume 11, 1874 July-December (Box 32)
  - Subgroup 7. Willow Ware Manufacturing Company, 1864-1873; 9 volumes
    Samuel Colt built his armory on a floodplain in Hartford's South Meadows. A dyke was built and thousands of willow trees planted to help prevent soil erosion. These willows were the inspiration, and the material, for Colt's Willow Ware Manufacturing Company. Founded circa 1864, the company used the abundant willows to manufacture furniture, baskets, and wagons. Colt brought skilled craftsmen and their families over from Germany to work in the Willow Ware plant. He built them a "company town", called Potsdam Village, complete with chalet-type housing and a beer garden. Fire destroyed the Willow Ware factory building in 1874. Due in part to increased competition, it was never rebuilt.
    - Financial Records, 1864-1873
      Items 3, 4, 5 are in one box.
      - Daybooks, 1868-1873; 2 volumes
        Although these volumes are labeled "daybooks" they do not contain standard daybook entries. They contain the Willow Ware Company's retail accounts and list the orders placed by these various merchants.
        The volumes are chronological by year, and within, chronological by month and year.
        - 1868 December-1873 October (Volume Item 1)
        - 1870 November-1873 April (Volume Item 2)
      - Checkbook, 1870 November-1873 March; 1 volume (Volume Item 3)
        Contains check stubs for checks written as well as some forty pages of blank checks.
        Stubs are in chronological order.
      - Inventories, 1864-1870; 2 volumes
        Contains year-end inventories of manufactured items, chairs, baskets, hampers etc., as well as some materials used in production. The first inventroy, 1864 December, was crossed out and consolidated in the second volume, 1864 December-1870 December.
        Chronological by year.
        - 1864 December (Volume Item 4)
        - 1864 December-1870 December (Volume Item 5)
      - Journals, 1864-1873; 2 volumes
        Contains a monthly accounting of the basic assets and liabilities for the Willow Ware plant.
        Organized in chronological order by month and year.
        - 1864 January-1871 May (Volume Item 6)
        - 1871 June-1873 October (Volume Item 7)
      - Ledger, 1864-1873; 1 volume (Volume Item 8)
        Contains the list of Willow Ware accounts and their debit/credit standing with the company. Index included at front and back of volume.
      - Petty Cash Book, 1872 January-1873 February; 1 volume (Volume Item 9)
        Contains the account of petty cash on hand for the Willow Ware Company.
        Chronological by month and year.
  - Subgroup 8. Baxter Steam Engine Company, 1871-1894 (Box 33)
    The Colt Company manufactured a number of products under contract from other companies in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. One of these was the Baxter Steam Engine. The Baxter Steam Engine Company was apparently purchased sometime in 1871 from the firm of Russell E Spheer and operated out of New York City. The Colt contract with the Company (Russell & Spheer) dates to September, 1870. Colt then transferred business to the new Baxter Steam Engine Co. at the request of Russell & Spheer. The Colt Company manufactured the engine, which in turn was sold by the Baxter Steam Engine Company and its agents.
    - Series 1. Outgoing Correspondence, 1871-1890 (Box 33)
      Contains the correspondence to the Colt Company from the Baxter Steam Engine Co. and its agents. Most of the correspondence is concerned with orders and the squaring of accounts between Baxter and Colt.
      It is arranged in chronological order by year and, within each folder, alphabetically by name of correspondent.
      - 1871-1874, 1877-1885, 13 folders (Box 33)
      - 1886-1890, 5 folders (Box 34)
    - Series 2. Incoming Correspondence, 1871-1873; 3 folders (Box 34)
      Contains a relatively small amount of correspondence from the Colt Company to Baxter Steam Engine. Most of the correspondence deals with the early period of the business relationship between the two companies and therefore concerns itself with setting down the terms under which the two companies would continue to do business.
      Arranged in chronological order by year, within that it is alphabetical by name of correspondent.
    - Series 3. Accounts, 1874-1881; 2 folders (Box 34)
      Contains an account between Baxter Steam Engine and the Colt Company of the total amount, in dollars, of engines sold and the royalties due the Baxter Steam Engine Company. Also, lists of engines sold and consigned to dealers. Includes horsepower designation.
      - Accounts, 1874-1881 (Box 34)
      - The following are in the same folder (Box 34)
        - Engines sold, 1871-1872 (Box 34)
        - Agent's stock, 1872 (Box 34)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 34)
      - Advertising cuts and circulars (Box 34)
      - Catalogues, 1878, 1880, 1889, 1894 (Box 34)
      - Weight of castings for canal boat (Box 34)
  - Subgroup 9. Colt's Disc Engine (West's Patent Disc Engine), 4 folders (Box 35)
    The Colt Disc Engine was another product manufactured under contract by Colt. The West Patent Disc Engine adopted the name of its manufacturer and was renamed Colt's Disc Engine.
    - Advertising cuts and circulars (Box 35)
    - Catalogues (Box 35)
    - Correspondence, 1878, 1880-1882, 1884, 1888 (Box 35)
    - Royalty and sales records of engines, 2 volumes (Box 35)
  - Subgroup 10. Facer Refrigerating and Ice Machine Company, 1 folder (Box 36)
    The Colt Company, in addition to the engines noted, manufactured other related machinery. The Facer Company of New York contracted for the manufacture of its refrigerating and ice machine.
    - Catalogue, undated (Box 36)
  - Subgroup 11. Federal Adding Machine Company, 1918-1924; 5 folders (Box 36)
    As part of the post-war diversification effort, Colt contracted with the Federal Adding Machine Company for production of its "A" adding machine. Production began at the Colt Company in 1919. The relationship between the two companies was something less than beneficial, especially for Colt, and production ceased circa 1923.
    - Letters of recommendation, 1918 (Box 36)
      About the machine prior to the manufacturing agreement.
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1920, 1922 (Box 36)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1919-1920, 1922 (Box 36)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 36)
      - Correspondence with Colt, 1919-1920 (Box 36)
      - Production notes, 1920, 1923 (Box 36)
      - Rebuilt machines, 1924 (Box 36)
    - The following are in the same folder (Box 36)
      - Legal papers, 1920-1922 (Box 36)
      - Stockholder's papers, 1919-1922 (Box 36)
      - Newspaper articles, 1921 (Box 36)
  - Subgroup 12. Gatling Gun Company, 1865-1900
    Dr. Richard J. Gatling was born in North Carolina in 1818. He gave up medicine to pursue inventions of a more mechanical nature. Tragically naive from the vantage point of the nuclear age, Gatling believed that a weapon of sufficient destructive capabilities, one that would result in an enormous loss of life, was sufficient to end wars. That weapon, he believed, was his Gatling Gun. It was the first hand-operated battery or rapid fire machine gun.
    Gatling began his work on the gun in Indianapolis in 1861-1862. In the fall of 1862, Gatling went to Cincinnati, where the manufacture of six guns by Miles Greenwood and Company was negotiated. Beginning in 1865, and until coming to Hartford, the Cooper Fire Arms Manufacturing Company of Philadelphia manufactured the Gatling Gun.
    Manufacture in Indianapolis ended in 1874. The Gatling Gun Company of Connecticut was formed and purchased, for the sum of $25,000, all the stock, property, and assets of the Gatling Gun Company of Indiana.
    The Gatling Gun Company of Connecticut was located at, and the guns manufactured by, the Colt Company of Hartford.
    See the Gatling file in the History section of Administrative File.
    - Series 1. Accounts, 1872-1889; 7 folders (Box 37)
      Contains accounts with retailers, inventories, financial report numbers of guns manufactured, and accounts of labor and materials.
      - Account with Paget & Co., 1872 (Box 37)
      - Guns manufactured, 1873-1874 (Box 37)
      - Labor/Materials, 1873-1874 (Box 37)
      - Account with Morgan & Co., 1875 (Box 37)
      - Inventories, 1875, 1876, 1888, 1889 (Box 37)
      - The following are in the same folder (Box 37)
        - Cash liabilities, 1873-1874 (Box 37)
        - Cash receipts and disbursements, 1889 (Box 37)
      - Royalty statement, 1896 (Box 37)
    - Series 2. Agents Records, 1869-1899; 8 folders (Box 37)
      Contains the agreements, contracts, correspondence, and some accounts of the agents that represented the Gatling Gun Company.
      Folders with material on the agents are arranged in chronological order.
      - L. Broadwell (Europe), 1869 (Box 37)
      - J.H. Brown (Mexico), 1869-1871 (Box 37)
      - Schuyler, Hartley & Graham, 1871 (Box 37)
      - B.H. Zerbe, 1873 (Box 37)
      - C. Cramp (Philadelphia), 1886 (Box 37)
      - E.H. Carmick & C. Colne (France), 1887 (Box 37)
      - F. Penfield (Europe), 1888 (Box 37)
      - Gatling Gun Limited, circa 1888-1899 (Box 37)
    - Series 3. Incoming Correspondence, 1865-1898; 11 folders (Box 37)
      Contains the correspondence addressed to the Gatling Gun Company in Hartford and includes the correspondence from Colt to the Gatling Gun Company. Also contained in this series are tests and reports on guns sent to the cmmpany.
      Arranged in chronological order and alphabetical within each year.
      - Tests and reports (Box 37)
        - 1865 (Box 37)
        - 1873 (Box 37)
        - undated (Box 37)
      - Incoming correspondence (Box 37)
        - 1867-1873 (Box 37)
        - 1875 (Box 37)
        - 1876, 1877, 1879 (Box 37)
        - 1884-1885 (Box 37)
        - 1888-1889 (Box 37)
        - 1890, 1895, 1898 (Box 37)
        - 1892 (Box 37)
        - 1895 (Box 37)
    - Series 4. Outgoing Correspondence, 1867-1895; 6 folders
      Arranged in chrolological order.
      - 1880-1884, 1 folder (Box 38)
        Contains the outgoing correspondence from the Gatling company to the Colt Company.
      - 1867-1875, 1877-1878, 1889-1890, 1894-1895, 5 folders (Box 38)
        Contains early outgoing correspondence from R.J. Gatling, the Gatling Gun Company of Indianapolis.
    - Series 5. Orders, 1866-1900
      Contains orders placed to the Colt Company for the manufacture of Gatling Guns.
      Arranged first by source of orders, i.e. Army Department, and within that it is chronological.
      - Orders to Colt's, 4 folders (Box 38)
        - 1874, 1877-1879 (Box 38)
        - 1880-1883 (Box 38)
        - 1885 (Box 38)
        - 1886-1890 (Box 38)
      - Payment notices, 1877-1886; 1 folder (Box 38)
      - U.S. Government (Box 39)
        - Appropriations, 1874 (Box 39)
        - Rules for inspection, 1875 (Box 39)
      - Bureau of Ordnance (Box 39)
        - U.S. Army (Box 39)
          - 1866 (Box 39)
          - 1873-1874 (Box 39)
          - 1875 (Box 39)
          - 1877 (Box 39)
          - 1878 (Box 39)
          - 1880, 1882 (Box 39)
          - 1889-1893 (Box 39)
          - 1889 (Box 39)
          - 1894-1895 (Box 39)
          - 1897 (Box 39)
          - 1899 (Box 39)
        - U.S. Navy (Box 39)
          - 1873-1884 (Box 39)
          - 1900 (Box 39)
        - War Department, 1871-1890 (Box 39)
      - U.S. Arsenals, 1873-1884 (Box 39)
      - National Guard, 1886-1890 (Box 39)
      - U.S. Ordnance Agency, 1877-1878 (Box 39)
      - Foreign Governments (Box 40)
        - Argentina, 1867 (Box 40)
        - Dutch Government, 1867 (Box 40)
        - Prussia, 1867 (Box 40)
        - Bavarian Arsenals, 1868 (Box 40)
        - Denmark, 1868 (Box 40)
        - Russia, 1869-1870 (Box 40)
        - Turkey, 1870 (Box 40)
        - Italy, 1872 (Box 40)
        - Spain, 1873 (Box 40)
        - Japan, 1874 (Box 40)
        - Tunisia, 1875 (Box 40)
        - France, 1878 (Box 40)
    - Series 6. Legal Records, 1866-1890; 13 folders
      Contains agreements for sale and/or manufacture, U.S. and foreign licenses for production abroad, power of attorney, power of patentee, statements to stockholders, proxies, a copy of the articles of incorportion, some early board meeting minutes, by-laws, and lists of stockholders.
      Arranged by type of record and within that, in chronological order.
      - Agreements (Box 40)
        - 1866 (Box 40)
        - 1870, 2 folders (Box 40)
        - 1870, 1875, 1881 (Box 40)
        - 1871 (Box 40)
        - 1889 (Box 40)
        - 1890 (Box 40)
        - U.S. Cartridge Co. (Box 40)
      - Licenses (Box 40)
        - 1871 (Box 40)
        - 1879 (Box 40)
      - Power of Attorney, 1875, 1888 (Box 40)
      - Power of Patentee, 1881 (Box 40)
      - Stockholder's records, 1873-1874, 1876, 1880, 1888-1889 (Box 40)
    - Series 7. Production Records, 1873-1874; 2 folders
      Contains one bound volume consisting of a record of the component parts for the C.30 Gatling Gun. Also drawings of component parts, made perhaps for patent applications.
      - M1895 Gatling Gun, 1873-1874 (Box 40)
      - Drawings (Box 40)
    - Series 8. Publications/Advertisements, 1865-1898; 2 folders (Box 40)
      Contains a mixed assortment of newsclippings, leaflets, price lists, illustrations, advertisements, and brief company histories.
  - Subgroup 13. Railway Register Manufacturing Company, 1873-1890; 7 folders
    Located in Buffalo, New York, the Railway Register Manufacturing Company produced punches for railway use.
    Correspondence is in chronological order by year and alphabetical within that by the last name of the correspondent.
    - Outgoing Correspondence, 1873-1874, 1877-1879, 1882-1890; 6 folders (Box 41)
      Most of the correspondence is addressed to the Colt Company. These letters are from agents and the main office in Buffalo concerning manufacture and shipments.
    - Newsclippings (Box 41)
  - Subgroup 14. The Thorne Cylindrical Type-setting Machine Company, 1 folder
    As suggested by the company name, the Thorne Cylindrical Type-setting Machine Company was involved in the production of composing and distributing machines. Manufactured in Hartford, presumably by Colt's.
    - Catalog, undated (Box 42)
  - Subgroup 15. The Universal Printing Press, 1874-1890
    The Universal Printing Machine, patented by Merritt Gally in 1869, was manufactured by the Colt Company under a contract made with three licensees of the press in 1873. The licensees traded under the name of E.V. Haughwout & Co.
    This license was terminated in 1876 and Colt continued to manufacture the printing presses for the patentee, Merritt Gally.
    In 1886, Gally's patent expired on the press and Colt continued to produce them for the J. Thomson Press Company. John Thomson had been Merritt Gally's manager. A legal battle followed between Gally and Thomson.
    - Outgoing Correspondence (Box 42)
      Contains almost exclusively outgoing correspondence from either Gally or Thomson to the Colt Company.
      - 1874, 1877-1886, 4 folders (Box 42)
      - 1886-1890, 5 folders (Box 43)
    - Incoming Correspondence (Box 43)
    - Legal (Box 43)
      Contains the defendants brief to the litigation between Gally and Thomson.
    - Catalogues (Box 43)
      Contains an advertising circular and four sales catalogues from J. Thomson Press Company.
- Legal File, circa 1831-1943; T001481; 6.50 cubic feet
  - Series 1. Agreements and Contracts, 1849-1899; 20 folders
    Arranged chronologically by year. No index. See item listing in first folder.
    For contracts dealing with arms manufacture, see Orders, Series 4, in Business File Also, Correspondence, Series 2 and 3 in Business File.
    - Agreements for Employment (Box 44)
      - 1849 (Box 44)
      - 1852 (Box 44)
      - 1853 (Box 44)
      - 1859 (Box 44)
      - 1867 (Box 44)
      - 1878 (Box 44)
      - 1894 (Box 44)
      - Undated (Box 44)
    - Agreements for Manufacture (Box 44)
      - 1870, 2 folders (Box 44)
      - 1871 (Box 44)
      - 1883 (Box 44)
      - 1890 (Box 44)
    - Agreements with Selling Firms (Box 44)
      - 1859 (Box 44)
      - 1860 (Box 44)
      - 1865 (Box 44)
      - 1866 (Box 44)
      - 1868, 1870, 1873 (Box 44)
      - 1896-1897, 1899 (Box 44)
    - Contract for Universal Printing Press, 1886 (Box 44)
  - Series 2. Charter, 1836; 1 folder
    The single item in this series is the charter for the "Patent Arms Manufacturing Company" of Paterson, New Jersey, 1836. Issued to Samuel Colt, et.al. One printed copy, 1836, and one photostatic copy, circa 1949.
    - Charter (Box 44)
  - Series 3. Complaints and Law Suits, 1851-1913
    See also, Correspondence, Series 2 and 3 in Business File.
    - Bills of Complaint (Box 44)
      Contains breach of contract cases and claims on unsold arms.
      Arranged chronologically by the date the complaint was first filed. No index. See item listing in first folder.
      - 1884 (Box 44)
      - 1908 (Box 44)
      - 1911 (Box 44)
    - Law Suits (Box 44)
      Contains files of suits by and against the Colt Company, in the U.S. and abroad. Files contain depositions and correspondence pertaining to cases.
      Law suits are arranged in chronological order by year.
      - 1851 (Box 44)
      - 1856 (Box 44)
      - 1857 (Box 44)
      - 1870, 2 folders (Box 44)
      - 1870 (German) (Box 44)
      - 1873 (Box 45)
      - 1877 (Box 45)
      - 1879 (Box 45)
      - 1882, 2 folders (Box 45)
      - 1884, 2 folders (Box 45)
      - 1885-1886 (Box 45)
      - 1887 (Box 45)
      - 1889 (Box 45)
      - 1890 (Box 45)
      - 1900 (Box 45)
      - 1911 (Box 45)
      - 1913 (Box 45)
  - Series 4. Patents, circa 1831-1943
    By 1920, the Colt Company owned or was licensed under 300 patents, 50 of which were design patents.
    The patent series contains information on both individual and company patents. Also includes one box of oversized drawings.
    - Applications, 1844-1856; 6 folders (Box 45)
      Contains the inventor's name and description of item a patent is requested for.
      Arranged chronologically by date filed. Item listing in first folder.
      - 1844 (Box 45)
      - 1849 (Box 45)
      - 1850 (Box 45)
      - 1851, 2 folders (Box 45)